<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Business on Dailey Missives</title><link>https://dailey.page/categories/business/</link><description>Recent content in Business on Dailey Missives</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dailey.page/categories/business/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>2024 in Retrospective</title><link>https://dailey.page/p/2024-in-retro/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dailey.page/p/2024-in-retro/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://dailey.page/p/2024-in-retro/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post 2024 in Retrospective" />&lt;h1 id="2024-retrospective-creo">2024 Retrospective (Creo)&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>When I ended my time at Stratasan in March of 2023, my original goal was to stick to a lighter working schedule that allowed me to spend more time with my (rather large-ish) family. After committing over a decade to a startup, I was ready for a change of pace for a time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I had two major goals in mind coming into 2024:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Make &amp;ldquo;small bets&amp;rdquo; on side projects that might gain traction (either on my own or with a business partner).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Leverage my experience in the healthcare B2B SaaS (yes, it&amp;rsquo;s very specific) sector to earn income.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In 2024, my only &amp;ldquo;small bet&amp;rdquo; was Calendaristic. I spent more time in the first quarter of the year on this than any other quarter. As my consulting work (under &lt;a class="link" href="https://creollc.co" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Creo Advisory&lt;/a>) became more demanding, side projects became more difficult to focus on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What else happened in 2024, broadly speaking?&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>I co-founded the &lt;a class="link" href="https://nashvillectoclub.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Nashville CTO Club&lt;/a> with Josh Segall and Jim Siegienski.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I started &lt;a class="link" href="https://techfounder.community" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Tech Founder Community&lt;/a> to try to connect with other engineering founders and co-founders.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I connected with a &lt;em>lot&lt;/em> of people in 2024. I continue to believe that this is the primary way that serendipity strikes. According to Google Calendar, I met with over 400 people in 2024. Calendly was a life-saver here.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Many conversations started off with a meeting at some local event (Haley Zapolski and Josh Segall hosted many of these) or events at the Nashville Entrepreneur Center.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A good many of these were referrals from folks I have worked with or for in the past. Referrals are the best compliment I can receive!&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="what-went-well">What went well?&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The Nashville CTO Club got off to a &lt;em>great&lt;/em> start in September. Kudos to Mr. Segall for being the primary driver of this thing. It&amp;rsquo;s obvious that Josh hosts a lot of events, because he though of a lot of details that I simply would not have considered. It gave this group needed structure.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The consulting / fractional business continued to do well. I was able to focus on clients that I felt I offerred the highest value (in my particular niche, relevant to my past experience) and turn down potential work for which I did not feel well-suited. A breakdown of how I billed categories is below. &amp;ldquo;P&amp;amp;E&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;Product and Engineering&amp;rdquo; - basically technical due diligence but for an organization instead of an investor.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://dailey.page/p/2024-in-retro/work-categories-2024.png"
width="1200"
height="742"
srcset="https://dailey.page/p/2024-in-retro/work-categories-2024_hu1f4c6aef101217d07a70c975565ae828_68047_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w, https://dailey.page/p/2024-in-retro/work-categories-2024_hu1f4c6aef101217d07a70c975565ae828_68047_1024x0_resize_box_3.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Breakdown of how I billed services in 2024."
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="161"
data-flex-basis="388px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>I was able to (mostly) stick to a four-day-a-week work schedule, which allowed me to prioritize more time with my family.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>About halfway through the year I found myself doing a lot of interviewing for CTO and VPoE roles (I was the interviewer on behalf of my client). Given that this was somewhat of a rarity when I worked at one company, I used the opportunity to leverage the repitition here in order to improve my interview process. As Annie Dukes said, you can&amp;rsquo;t just gain experience by letting things wash over you; you have to be intentional about it! I feel like intentionally improving on my interviewing skills bore fruit.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="what-didnt-go-well">What didn&amp;rsquo;t go well?&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The Tech Founder Community languished. In June, it seemed like a doable thing. In July, baby #6 joined our family and I had forgotten just how much a new baby can take the wind out of your sails (especially in your forties!).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I spent so much time on Creo Advisory that I failed to get any other side projects off of the ground.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="what-are-my-goals-for-2025">What are my goals for 2025?&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>I will launch three side projects into production in 2025. Two of these are known and in-progress. The third is a TBD.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I will block off more time for reading and writing. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to spend so much time on the application (consulting, building) that no time is spent learning and reflecting.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I&amp;rsquo;ll promote useful engagement within the Tech Founder Community, further refining it&amp;rsquo;s purpose and mission.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="other-thoughts">Other Thoughts&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Presumably, I&amp;rsquo;m often hired as fractional CTO to help with the engineering team. But often I find that I spend more time with company leadership thinking about business strategy. Business strategy affects engineering strategy and vice versa. This is something that I enjoyed and would love to do more of. However, I&amp;rsquo;m not really sure if I want to market myself as some kind of strategic advisor!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="bonus-favorite-business-related-books-of-the-year">Bonus: Favorite business-related books of the year?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This one is easy! &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/199798096-everything-is-predictable?ac=1&amp;amp;from_search=true&amp;amp;qid=ptdQJPGaYc&amp;amp;rank=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Everything is Predictable&lt;/a> by Tom Chivers and &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/35957157-thinking-in-bets" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Thinking in Bets&lt;/a> by Annie Dukes. The former I found via &lt;a class="link" href="https://fivebooks.com/best-books/best-popular-science-books-2024-royal-society-book-prize-john-hutchison/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Five Books&lt;/a> and the latter was via a conversation with &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/prakashsripathy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Prakesh Sripathy&lt;/a>. I am a fan of being uncertain and both of these books help think through uncertainty. I&amp;rsquo;ll write more about these too books later!&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Photo by &lt;a class="link" href="https://unsplash.com/@hariprasad000?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Hari Nandakumar&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>The Wide World of the Fractional CTO</title><link>https://dailey.page/p/wide-world-of-the-fractional-cto/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dailey.page/p/wide-world-of-the-fractional-cto/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://dailey.page/p/wide-world-of-the-fractional-cto/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Wide World of the Fractional CTO" />&lt;p>Since leaving &lt;a class="link" href="https://dailey.page/p/hello-world" >Stratasan (acquired by Syntellis) in March of
2023&lt;/a> I started out doing some &lt;a class="link" href="http://localhost:1313/p/creo-advisory-llc/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>advisory and technical due
diligence work&lt;/a> for investors.
I&amp;rsquo;m still doing advisory and diligence work, but I&amp;rsquo;ve also found demand for my
help as a fractional CTO.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="whats-a-fractional-cto">What&amp;rsquo;s a fractional CTO?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>You might as well ask, &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s a Chief Technology Officer (CTO)?&amp;rdquo; It varies a
lot from company to company (based on size, structure, and type of product) but
in general &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief_technology_officer" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Wikipedia has a satisfactory
(although wordy)
answer&lt;/a>. If I had to
boil it down, I&amp;rsquo;d say that &amp;ldquo;the CTO makes sure that the technology strategy
aligns well with the business strategy and executes the technology strategy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A fractional CTO does much of the same thing, but on a part-time (fractional)
basis, often working with more than one company at a time. Just like a full-time
CTO, a fractional CTO will often specialize in one industry or company stage of
growth.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In my case, I work often with startups and early stage companies in the
healthcare sector. There are three things that make my career relevant to this
particular niche:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>I have a amassed a wide range of experience in the healthcare sector across nearly a quarter century (I got my start in 2000).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I have spent most of my career in startups and early stage companies in New
York and Nashville, and have myself been a co-founder with a successful nine-figure exit.
I know excatly what it&amp;rsquo;s like to wear all of the hats, find product-market
fit, and scale a team!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Given my experience with technical due diligence (on both ends of the
transaction), I am familiar with the markers that investors are looking for
in a company.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The confluence of these three areas of experience have left me well suited to
serve as an advisor to the non-technical founders and leadership of startups.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Technology strategy has a give-and-take relationship with business strategy
My job is to fully understand and internalize the business strategy, determine
technical feasibility, and then build a roadmap that combines the two.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-kinds-of-things-do-you-do-as-a-fractional-cto">What kinds of things do you do as a fractional CTO?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Honestly, it&amp;rsquo;s all over the map (hence the title of this, &amp;ldquo;the wide world&amp;rdquo;!),
and that&amp;rsquo;s one of the things that I love about it. Here are some examples of
projects that I have done over the summer:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Diagnose the current reality (what we have) and identify gaps based on the
business strategy (what we need) and build a roadmap to get there. This has
ranged from early stage startups (the whole business runs in an Excel
spreadsheet!) to scaling growth companies.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Advise companies that are looking to hire their first full time engineer and
subsequent team members. This covers everything from sourcing leads,
interviewing, hiring, and then advising them while they ramp up.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Perform a &amp;ldquo;pre-sale inspection&amp;rdquo; for early stage companies. In short, I
evaluate them as an investor might do in order to best prepare them for a
transaction.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I write more about the variety of things I do &lt;a class="link" href="https://creollc.co/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Usually, any engagement with a company lasts only 2-3 months. My goal is not to
embed myself in an organization forever: I&amp;rsquo;m there to help build a plan, get
things on track, and coach the team as needed.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="how-do-i-know-if-i-need-a-fractional-cto">How do I know if I need a fractional CTO?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>There are a few signs that it might be useful to bring on an fCTO:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Your primary product is a SaaS tool, but no one on the leadership team has technology
experience.&lt;/strong> A fractional CTO can work on your side of the table to make sure
that the technology roadmap supports the business strategy, that any
outsourced development work is not incurring unnecessary technology debt, and
to keep the momentum going.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Your development lead is highly technical, but not strategic.&lt;/strong> An fCTO can
help your team think more strategically and balance the technology roadmap
with the business&amp;rsquo;s needs.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>You need a CTO, but you can&amp;rsquo;t afford one full-time.&lt;/strong> A fractional hire may
be what you need to fit your budget.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Your technology roadmap has gone off track.&lt;/strong> You need an experienced leader
to diagnose the problem, recommend new processes, and get things back on
track quickly.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>You anticipate a business milestone&lt;/strong> (e.g., a round of funding, an
aquisition, or a major new product). An experienced fCTO can help you avoid
pitfalls and build a plan for success.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="i-need-a-fractional-cto-how-do-i-get-in-touch">I need a fractional CTO! How do I get in touch?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Shoot me an email (brian at this domain). I am always happy to chat, and if I&amp;rsquo;m
not a good fit I may know someone who is!&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Header generated by &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bing.com/images/create?FORM=GDPGLP" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Bing Image
Creator&lt;/a> on October 26, 2023.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;a man working on a laptop on top of a globe of the world in an
impressionistic style&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>Why Calendaristic?</title><link>https://dailey.page/p/why-calendaristic/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dailey.page/p/why-calendaristic/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://dailey.page/p/why-calendaristic/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Why Calendaristic?" />&lt;p>From 2011 to 2019, the engineering team at Stratasan (where I served as CTO) worked
from home at most once a week. In March of 2020, that all changed and we went
100% distributed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like many small companies in the before-times, we worked out of an office with
a small number of conference rooms. We used shared calendars to book the
rooms. If a meeting went over time, participants had to wrap up and
exit so the new meeting could get started.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This served as a forcing function in a few ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The availability of meeting rooms put an artificial ceiling on the number of
meetings we could have at any time.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Meetings had to end on time so the room could be made available for the next
group.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Recurring meetings were trickier to set up because one needed to check for room
availability.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Meetings were also &lt;em>visible&lt;/em>. You could see when folks were huddling (whether in
a conference room or at a desk).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m neutral on whether the above is good or bad. But it did serve to make
meetings more scarce, and scarcity increases value. If you have fewer meetings,
it forces you to be more intentional with how the time is spent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When we left the office, all of that disappeared.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Meetings proliferated (anecdotally, but with some data to back it
up). In particular, &lt;em>recurring&lt;/em> meetings seemed to proliferate.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Meetings went over time more frequently. &amp;ldquo;Does anyone here have a hard stop?&amp;rdquo;
became a common question.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Meetings seemed to carry a higher cognitive load on participants.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>We did a lot to try to mitigate some of what we were seeing. Several of us
configured &amp;ldquo;speedy meetings&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. We performed periodic &amp;ldquo;recurring meeting
resets&amp;rdquo; where we cleared recurring meetings and only set up the ones we thought
were absolutely necessary. We encouraged detailed agendas. We set up a
&amp;ldquo;one-pager&amp;rdquo; that detailed &lt;em>how we do meetings&lt;/em> in order to try to make them more
efficient.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I think some of this worked. But I can&amp;rsquo;t be sure, because the data either didn&amp;rsquo;t
exist or was very tedious to gather. We could get some calendar statistics by doing spot checks.
I could look at my calendar as well as some of my team members. There is &lt;em>some&lt;/em>
calendar analytics built into the Google Workspace dashboard, but it was too
high level to really get any useful information from.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What I really wanted was a nice dashboard to monitor how we were doing. In
particular, I wanted to trend it over time. I had many questions. Among them:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Is our meeting burden (average per person) trending up or down?
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>How high is &lt;em>too&lt;/em> high?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Break it down by recurring versus one-offs.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>How many meetings have an agenda? How many have a &lt;em>good&lt;/em> agenda?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Break down averages in a few ways:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>By department.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>By internal vs. external participants.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Since &amp;ldquo;speedy meetings&amp;rdquo; are only configurable on the account level, who are
the folks who are not taking advantage of that setting?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>There are lots of other questions I want to answer, but these are the ones I
started with.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are lots of great calendar tools out there. But all of them, in my
experience, are targeted at the &lt;em>individual user&lt;/em>, not operators. I wanted a
tool that would look at my Google Workspace domain and run the analytics on
everyone in the company, not just me and/or my team.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since I haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to find such a tool, I&amp;rsquo;m building it in
&lt;a class="link" href="https://calendaristic.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Calendaristic&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am looking for a handful of companies that can test this with me as it&amp;rsquo;s being
developed. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested, please head over to the &lt;a class="link" href="https://calendaristic.com/signup/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>sign up
page&lt;/a> to let me know you&amp;rsquo;re interested! Even
if this doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound like a product you&amp;rsquo;d want, if you have thoughts about
meetings in general and want to chat, hit me up! My email is &lt;code>brian at this domain&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Photo by &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->Gaining Visuals&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> on &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->Unsplash&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Cognitive load&amp;rdquo; of video conferencing has been written about
elsewhere, but the good news is that it was one of the easier things to
alleviate. Tips on this can be found
&lt;a class="link" href="https://news.stanford.edu/2021/02/23/four-causes-zoom-fatigue-solutions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>here&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>60 minute meetings become 50 minute meetings, 30 minute meetings
become 25 minute meetings. This is configurable in Google Calendar for users.
More information can be found
&lt;a class="link" href="https://blog.google/products/calendar/make-most-your-day-7-google-calendar-tips/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>here&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Creo Advisory, LLC - Advisory and Technical Diligence</title><link>https://dailey.page/p/creo-advisory-llc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dailey.page/p/creo-advisory-llc/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://dailey.page/p/creo-advisory-llc/creo-color-no-bg.svg" alt="Featured image of post Creo Advisory, LLC - Advisory and Technical Diligence" />&lt;p>After wrapping up more than a decade at Stratasan, I&amp;rsquo;m now working with startup
and early stage companies as an advisor as well as providing technical due
diligence to investors. My work is performed with &lt;a class="link" href="https://creollc.co" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Creo Advisory,
LLC&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="advisory-work">Advisory Work&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>While at &lt;a class="link" href="https://dailey.page/p/hello-world" >Stratasan&lt;/a> I found myself doing a lot of things I
hadn&amp;rsquo;t done before (as one does when you grow a company from two to about
a hundred employees). Going from engineer to lead engineer to manager to manager
of managers meant that about every two years my job description changed
drastically.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To keep up, I did an inordinate amount of reading. I also relied heavily on
discussions with peers. One thing that I found extremely useful was finding
trusted advisors to work with. They served as both experienced voices and
trusted soundboards. Often I had an idea of what I needed to do, I just needed
to walk through it with someone and have them tell me, &amp;ldquo;Yeah, that makes sense.
No, you&amp;rsquo;re not crazy.&amp;rdquo; Having an advisor not otherwise tied to the company would
also extract me from the day-to-day grind and help me see the larger strategy.
In short, I found having advisors to be very valuable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve also &lt;em>served&lt;/em> as an advisor to other companies. Given how engaged I was at
Stratasan, I could not do this as much as I would have liked. Post-exit, I have
more time to devote to this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One interesting thing about advisors is that the same advisor is not always
useful in every situation. Each time I found a good advisor, there was a process
of determining the subject matter expertise I needed most (product management?
security/compliance? engineering?) and reviewing potential candidates for
personality fit. I have worked with some folks who I was able to help for a time
and after a while they no longer needed what I could provide. Advisor
relationships are rarely permanent, and it&amp;rsquo;s important for the advisor and
advisee to know when it&amp;rsquo;s no longer worth the investment of time.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="technical-due-diligence">Technical Due Diligence&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been through a handful of technical due diligence processes. During each
one, I always thought about ways to make it easier on the prospective company.
They varied from &amp;ldquo;Wow, that felt entirely cursory&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;Holy smokes, this goes
into a very unnecessary level of detail!&amp;rdquo; I hope to leverage this experience to
run a technical due diligence process that minimizes the time necessary from the prospective
company as well as maximizing usefulness for the investor or acquiring company.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-makes-_you_-qualified">What makes &lt;em>you&lt;/em> qualified?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s a fair question! There are a couple attributes that make both an advisor or technical reviewer successful:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;em>A wide base of underlying experience.&lt;/em> I have worked in technology since
2000, giving me almost a quarter of a century of experience across a wide
array of startups across many technology stacks and industries.
Much of what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned about successfully running
teams is applicable to pretty much any industry independent of the specific
technology stack.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>A history as an operator.&lt;/em> Many consultants and advisors purport to have
some kind of system or process that will resolve all your business problems
(the proverbial &amp;ldquo;silver bullet&amp;rdquo;). Rarely do these folks have &lt;em>actual
experience operating a business.&lt;/em> The best advisors and investors that I&amp;rsquo;ve
worked with all had prior experience as an operator.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="ideal-project">Ideal project?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Given my experience, I&amp;rsquo;m better suited to working as an advisor or doing
technical diligence on startup and early stage companies with 5-100 employees.
My domain expertise is heavily in healthcare and my technical experience is
focused predominately on open-source stacks.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="great-how-do-i-find-out-more-or-get-in-touch">Great, how do I find out more or get in touch?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To find out more about Creo, see &lt;a class="link" href="https://creollc.co" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you think I might be helpful with whatever enterprise you&amp;rsquo;ve got going on,
you can get in touch with me &lt;a class="link" href="https://forms.gle/sttrRx9LgJisnorSA" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Celebrate the Skeptics</title><link>https://dailey.page/p/celebrate-the-skeptics/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dailey.page/p/celebrate-the-skeptics/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://dailey.page/p/celebrate-the-skeptics/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Celebrate the Skeptics" />&lt;p>I read a recent post from &lt;a class="link" href="https://medium.com/@royrapoport/being-right-doesnt-matter-70f00e2cd2a4" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Roy Rapoport titled, &amp;ldquo;Being Right Doesn&amp;rsquo;t Matter.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> I&amp;rsquo;ll probably butcher it by summarizing it in one line, so I suggest you go read it first (it&amp;rsquo;s only a few paragraphs). Ultimately, he makes the point that &amp;ldquo;being right doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter if you can&amp;rsquo;t build consensus.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I wholeheartedly agree with this. As I was reading his post, I was reminded of a recent story that I heard on EconTalk&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> about a Hungarian physician and scientist, &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ignaz_Semmelweis" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Ignaz Semmelweis&lt;/a>. He noted that the doctors&amp;rsquo; ward had triple the mortality rate as the midwives&amp;rsquo; ward in his obstetric clinic. At the time, it was normal for doctors to carve up a cadaver in the morgue, wear the blood proudly on their apron (it was a badge to indicate just how hard they were working), and go straight to the labor and delivery rooms. Cleanliness was simply not a priority. Semmelweis noted that if he washed his hands in chlorinated lime solution the patient mortality rate dropped to 1%.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He accumulated some evidence to back up his claims and published, hoping to save tens of thousands of lives. However, his claims were not well received. The wider medical field rejected Semmelweis&amp;rsquo;s claims and his impact was not as significant as he had hoped. Semmelwies died at 47 of blood poisoning in an insane asylum just a few years prior to his ideas becoming more widely accepted.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some of this reaction might be due to what Megan McArdle called the &amp;ldquo;Oedipus trap&amp;rdquo; (humans have a hard time reconciling the fact that their decisions may have caused a significant amount of harm, even if they were unintentional). It didn&amp;rsquo;t help that Semmelweis had a reputation of being a difficult guy to work with. He considered himself very smart and felt that his experimental studies should have been sufficient to convince others that he was right.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&amp;hellip; Dr. Semmelwies also didn&amp;rsquo;t do himself any favors. [&amp;hellip;] He went out of his
way to attack doctors who rejected his thesis, devoting a full sixty-four
pages of one of his publications to attack a single obstetrician from Prague
who questioned his results.&lt;/em>&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This scenario is much more dramatic than anything we’d run into (we’re rarely contradicting the popular opinion of an entire profession) but if we agree that &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Groupthink" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>group think&lt;/a> is bad, then we can agree that there are advantages for organizations to have a dissenting voice. It&amp;rsquo;s what Todd Kashdan delightfully calls &amp;ldquo;principled insubordination.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>With a single rebel airing alternate and unpopular views, a group reduces its
confirmation bias and motivated reasoning and increases its creative
output.&lt;/em>&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In Kashdan&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Art of Insubordination,&amp;rdquo; he spends the first few chapters
presenting all of the evidence that &lt;em>we need skeptics.&lt;/em> This is especially true in any organization where
the work involves both creativity and complexity. Creative and complex endeavors (which applies to most product-first organizations)
benefit from people who are willing to speak up in situations where they may be contradicting popular opinion (&amp;ldquo;group think&amp;rdquo;).
Skeptical viewpoints can encourage more thoughtful discussion.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, the issue is that many organizations do not &lt;em>encourage&lt;/em> skepticism. On
the contrary, they often suppress it. If you&amp;rsquo;ve seen a leader respond
defensively to a question asked in good faith, then you&amp;rsquo;ve seen this happen.
&lt;a class="link" href="https://freakonomics.com/podcast/how-to-make-meetings-less-terrible-ep-389/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Unhealthy peace&lt;/a>
is often prioritized over healthy conflict. Furthermore, it only takes is one
poor reaction to a challenging question to effectively silence all future questions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This leads to an environment where only the boldest or most adversarial team
members will express skepticism. In short: &lt;em>if an environment is hostile to
dissenting opinions, then the only dissenting opinions will be hostile.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ergo, we need to build environments where contrary opinions are welcomed and
rewarded so that we can benefit from sharper critical thinking from our teams.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What can you as a manager or leader do to encourage principled insubordination?
Here are four specific things.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>First, be vulnerable. This take courage and is often uncomfortable. Brene Brown really does a great job of explaining this in &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40109367-dare-to-lead" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Dare To Lead&lt;/a>. Leadership must demonstrate that they can’t know all of the things and that they are open to changing course. If leadership is not open to criticism, they will receive none, and the organization will be worse for it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Coach. There’s a fine line between being a skeptic (challenging commonly accepted opinions, good) and a cynic (believing that others are not acting in good faith, bad). A cynical person might be recovering from a previous job where they were not able to ask (or, worse, punished for asking) critical questions, but with the right encouragement they might be converted into a skeptic. Other team members might just need a little help challenging opinions in a diplomatic, constructive way.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Solicit. Solicitation of feedback is often required because many people are reluctant to provide honest feedback because they&amp;rsquo;ve learned that leaders don’t react well. Keeping your head down is a good strategy in many organizations, so you have to work to solicit dissenting opinions.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reward. Even solicitation may not be effective if some team members have had poor experiences raising objections in the past. Hence, rewarding those that speak up is critical as it signals to everyone else that disagreement is encouraged. Asking for clarification, seeking to understand, answering questions in good faith and, most importantly, changing course when merited: all of this indicates to the team that managers and leaders are open to constructive feedback.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>This short list might make it sound easy, but as any leader would know, it is most certainly not. A rush of adrenaline is a fundamental human reaction to contradiction, propelling us toward a vigorous verbal defense. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to tamp that immediate reaction down and listen. Listening can take the form of asking clarifying questions, surfacing the underlying problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once those voices have been heard and addressed in good faith, then the team can move on, even if it means that some parties have to &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disagree_and_commit" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>disagree and commit&lt;/a>. By being vulnerable, coaching, soliciting opinions, and rewarding dissent organizations can continue to benefit from critical thinking and avoid the trap of artificial consensus.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>(You might be saying, &amp;ldquo;Alright, that&amp;rsquo;s all well and good, Brian, what if I&amp;rsquo;m not a manager? What if I am the skeptic?&amp;rdquo; Well, carry on, I say! If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for ways to be more effective, then I recommend checking out &amp;ldquo;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57559387-the-art-of-insubordination" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>The Art of Insubordination: How to Dissent and Defy Effectively&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; by Todd Kashdan.)&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Photo from &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bing.com/images/create?FORM=GDPGLP" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Bing Image Creator&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.econtalk.org/megan-mcardle-on-the-oedipus-trap/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>March 20, 2023 EconTalk episode with Megan McArdle&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>Quote from Kashdan, &amp;ldquo;The Art of Insubordination, page 64.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>Quote from Kashdan, &amp;ldquo;The Art of Insubordination, page 53.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Books That Influenced Me (Business Edition)</title><link>https://dailey.page/p/books-that-influenced-me/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dailey.page/p/books-that-influenced-me/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://dailey.page/p/books-that-influenced-me/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Books That Influenced Me (Business Edition)" />&lt;p>As I am nearing the end of my tenure at the company I co-founded a decade ago, I
thought it would be useful to share some of the books that were influential to
me as I went from engineer to a lead-of-leads.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="code-completehttpswwwgoodreadscombookshow4845code_complete-by-steve-mcconnell">&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/4845.Code_Complete" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Code Complete&lt;/a> by Steve McConnell&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://dailey.page/p/books-that-influenced-me/code-complete.jpg"
width="318"
height="388"
srcset="https://dailey.page/p/books-that-influenced-me/code-complete_hu7540ff28651a1c84c58b83c4d6dddea5_20101_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w, https://dailey.page/p/books-that-influenced-me/code-complete_hu7540ff28651a1c84c58b83c4d6dddea5_20101_1024x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Code Complete"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="81"
data-flex-basis="196px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This book probably feels a bit dated as it was published in 2004. However, I
found this very useful early in my engineering career as I was learning to build
systems that were maintainable and useful. Some of the maxims that McConnell
included in this book are true no matter the language. For example, &amp;ldquo;write
programs for people first, computers second.&amp;rdquo; I often had a tendency to get
clever with code rather than trying to be blindingly obvious; being clever
tended to produce more pain (both for myself and others) down the road.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-mythical-man-month-essays-on-software-engineeringhttpswwwgoodreadscombookshow13629the_mythical_man_month-by-fred-brooks">&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13629.The_Mythical_Man_Month" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>The Mythical Man Month: Essays on Software Engineering&lt;/a> by Fred Brooks&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://dailey.page/p/books-that-influenced-me/mythical-man-month.jpg"
width="269"
height="400"
srcset="https://dailey.page/p/books-that-influenced-me/mythical-man-month_hud87a6cb5435090c6c871e4f8ade7831e_39892_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w, https://dailey.page/p/books-that-influenced-me/mythical-man-month_hud87a6cb5435090c6c871e4f8ade7831e_39892_1024x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Mythical Man Month"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="67"
data-flex-basis="161px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This book makes &amp;ldquo;Code Complete&amp;rdquo; feel quite young as &amp;ldquo;Mythical&amp;rdquo; was written in 1975. However, it&amp;rsquo;s commentary on software development is still timeless (if one can overlook some of the underlying sexism prevalent at the time). Two essays stuck with me more than others.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No_Silver_Bullet" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&amp;ldquo;There&amp;rsquo;s No Silver Bullet&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> highlighted accidental complexity versus essential complexity. Much work has been done to address accidental complexity (especially since 1975!) but essential complexity, the complexity of the underlying problems that we&amp;rsquo;re trying to solve, will always be with us. This one stuck with me because non-engineering types are &lt;em>constantly&lt;/em> enamoured by &amp;ldquo;silver bullets&amp;rdquo; - whether it&amp;rsquo;s data science, machine learning, artificial intelligence, or whatever is coming next. Whenever they come upon a hard problem they ask, &amp;ldquo;Why don&amp;rsquo;t we just use [the silver bullet]?&amp;rdquo; Even engineers like myself can fall prey to this way of thinking. The trouble is that these bullets rarely address &lt;em>the complexity of the underlying problem space&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mythical_Man-Month#The_mythical_man-month" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&amp;ldquo;The Mythical Man Month&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> Brooks asserts that &amp;ldquo;adding manpower to a late software project makes it later.&amp;rdquo; He highlights the importance of team communication in complex projects and provides a formula to demonstrate that more people means more and more communication overhead. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard this described by someone else as &amp;ldquo;clinks versus drinks.&amp;rdquo; If you sit at a bar with three people, you clink three times and then you can drink. But as you add more and more people to the party, all of your time is spent clinking with very little time for drinking!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-nature-of-software-developmenthttpswwwgoodreadscombookshow25254918-the-nature-of-software-development-by-ron-jeffries">&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25254918-the-nature-of-software-development" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>The Nature of Software Development&lt;/a> by Ron Jeffries&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://dailey.page/p/books-that-influenced-me/nature-of-software-development.jpg"
width="318"
height="381"
srcset="https://dailey.page/p/books-that-influenced-me/nature-of-software-development_hu72cc00ba6198d6b7229fc58a6495adb3_23701_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w, https://dailey.page/p/books-that-influenced-me/nature-of-software-development_hu72cc00ba6198d6b7229fc58a6495adb3_23701_1024x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="The Nature of Software Development"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="83"
data-flex-basis="200px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ron Jeffries is one of the original signatories of the &lt;a class="link" href="https://agilemanifesto.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>agile
manifesto&lt;/a>. The manifesto has been pillaged and
plundered by consultants until it has become &lt;a class="link" href="https://scaledagileframework.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>something completely
unrecognizable&lt;/a> from the original intent.
This book brings it all back home. We&amp;rsquo;re just here to deliver value to our
customers!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Stratasan and product and engineering teams read this as a group at least
twice. I found it to be extremely useful to help everyone get on the same page
about how a product-first company delivers value to customers. It helped us use
similar vocabulary (&amp;ldquo;tall and skinnies!&amp;rdquo; meaning high value, low cost). This
book was particularly useful because it explains the &lt;em>process&lt;/em> of software
development so well that you don&amp;rsquo;t actually need to be a developer to understand
it. That makes it much more useful for development-adjacent roles like product
management, QA, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="inspiredhttpswwwgoodreadscombookshow35249663-inspired-by-marty-cagan-and-chris-jones">&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/35249663-inspired" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Inspired&lt;/a> by Marty Cagan and Chris Jones&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Speaking of product management, this book and &amp;ldquo;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/55954021-empowered" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Empowered&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;
are aimed more at product managers. The Stratasan team read both of these books
as a group and I found them to be extremely helpful to communicate the vision
for a true product-first company.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If &amp;ldquo;The Nature of Software Development&amp;rdquo; was a good introduction to software
development for product managers, &amp;ldquo;Inspired&amp;rdquo; was a great introduction to product
management for software developers.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="acceleratehttpswwwgoodreadscombookshow35747076-accelerate-by-forsgren-humble-and-kim">&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/35747076-accelerate" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Accelerate&lt;/a> by Forsgren, Humble, and Kim&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>One of my biggest gripes with most &amp;ldquo;business&amp;rdquo; books is that they rarely have
data to back them up. Instead, they tend to rely on overly cute anecdotes to
emphasize or validate their assertions. &amp;ldquo;Accelerate&amp;rdquo; does not make this mistake.
You might be able to point out issues with their data collection (that&amp;rsquo;s beyond
my pay grade) but they certainly have the data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This book highlights the engineering metrics that correlate best with successful
organizations, based on annual surveys performed by the authors. They boil it
down to four key metrics. I&amp;rsquo;m not a fan of metrics for the sake of metrics, but
they make a very good case that these four metrics are really the ones you want
to watch.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-managers-pathhttpswwwgoodreadscombookshow33369254-the-manager-s-path-by-camille-fournier">&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/33369254-the-manager-s-path" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>The Manager&amp;rsquo;s Path&lt;/a> by Camille Fournier&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This book is broken out in a way that matches the trajectory of most careers in engineering management: from
individual contributor, to team lead, to manager of a single team, to multiple
teams, and then finally a manager of managers. This was a book I constantly kept
on hand as our company grew and I found myself referencing it often.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="high-output-managementhttpswwwgoodreadscomisbookshow324750high_output_management-by-andrew-grove">&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/is/book/show/324750.High_Output_Management" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>High Output Management&lt;/a> by Andrew Grove&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I found the title of this book off-putting at first. Some of the anecdotes and
recommendations are a bit heavy on the manufacturing side (not necessarily
suitable advice for the creative endeavor of a product company). However, it&amp;rsquo;s
good advice outweighed the anachronisms. It helped me understand a lot of the
reasoning behind OKRs. The single thing I took from this book: as a manager,
you&amp;rsquo;re no longer responsible for &lt;em>your&lt;/em> work; you&amp;rsquo;re now responsible for your
team&amp;rsquo;s work. Your job is now to help your team grow. I found this helpful as I
was transitioning from an individual contributor, because I still was very
tempted to measure my success based on &lt;em>my&lt;/em> output, not my teams. Trying to
balance individual output and managing a team is a miserable existence: this
book got me out of that hole.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tractionhttpswwwgoodreadscombookshow18886376-traction-by-gino-wickman">&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18886376-traction" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Traction&lt;/a> by Gino Wickman&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This book might feel like the odd-one out in this anthology, but I include it
because it had a &lt;em>huge&lt;/em> influence on how we ran the day-to-day business at Stratasan.
Neither Jason Moore (CEO) nor myself had ever scaled a company to a hundred
people. This book and EOS helped us to set up a good cadence of meetings and
communication between the various teams. It allowed us to set the strategy,
execute on it, and bubble up issues more quickly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We eventually moved away from stick adherence to EOS, but it served us well as
a solid foundation.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-about-you">What about you?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>These are the books that I found to be most helpful during Stratasan&amp;rsquo;s growth.
How about you? What books were instrumental in your professional growth? Leave a
comment or shoot me an email (brian at this domain).&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Photo by &lt;a class="link" href="https://unsplash.com/@tom_hermans" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Tom Hermans&lt;/a> on &lt;a class="link" href="https://unsplash.com/photos/9BoqXzEeQqM" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Unsplash&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item></channel></rss>